um so on behalf of St belon Hills uh I'd
like
to uh read a welcoming that we use in
one of our
services uh and the title of this
welcoming is
beware here we practice the inclusive
Gospel of
Jesus Christ
this means that you may be gathering
with tax
collectors
thieves adulterers
Hypocrites women as well as
men female male
priests gays and
lesbians the disabled the dying Native
Americans Mexicans Asians blacks and
other ethnic
minorities Bishops bigots her
agnostics
atheists Jews Muslims Hindus
Buddhists and strangers from foreign
lands anyone like those with whom Jesus
met so beware this is not an exclusive
club we welcome you
all so um
tonight's uh event is part of a series
um there we we do this thing every
Sunday at the disal church called the
Eucharist um we take Bread and Wine and
uh and we
celebrate and uh it being something that
we do frequently
regularly um it it becomes habitual and
so uh we put together this series with
the
intent of seeing the familiar routine
through new
eyes and so with that in mind we've
invited uh rabbis
Buddhists feminists
literalists atheists historians to come
and speak about the
Eucharist it's it's likely that if you
come to all of our teachings you're
going to hear something that will make
you
uncomfortable and and that's okay that's
the whole point we're we're trying to be
very provocative
here um but in being provocative we we
need to lay out some ground rules and so
the Rules of Engagement
are we we ask that everyone respect each
other uh asking questions is perfectly
fine but advice giving or telling people
what their problem is
is so tonight we have a great blessing
tonight G mik is going to speak to us
about uh about the Eucharist and Eastern
perspectives on Christianity G Michael
is the founder and spiritual director of
D mountain university in your Arizona
he's born in Los Angeles in
1952 and grew up in the Episcopal
church and I understand he was on a path
to becoming Episcopal priest and wound
up studying Tibetan Buddhism for 22
years in New Jersey in Southern
India uh G Michael was ordained a
Buddhist monk in
1983 and received the title of G in
1995 um
so with that I I guess we're going to
begin with some music and then uh and
then a teaching so welcome
[Applause]
[Music]
for
oh
[Music]
l
[Applause]
[Music]
call me
my
[Music]
R until the Son of
God come
[Music]
to and J us
and our shadows
[Music]
through shall come to the
time
[Music]
he
in one the hearts of
[Music]
all and be yourself the
king of King
[Music]
might want
the until the son of God
[Music]
oh
[Applause]
sh for
hi is that Lou enough can you
hear let's
do oh
better yeah
okay then uh tonight's
um you know I I'm very grateful to be
invited to talk about the Eucharist um
and I had to Google
Eucharist uh to know what I was going to
talk about
uh but uh no I I you know as as many of
you know I grew up in Phoenix and uh
went to All Saints Episcopal church and
you know a lot of people that come to me
with their horror stories about church
and for me it was just wonderful you
know for me uh church was
something really really beautiful and we
had really amazing priests at the church
and we had a beautiful church and the
garden in the church was uh very
beautiful M and many Havey times there
and uh I think for me
uh the best time was was Eucharist time
uh which in the Catholic church we call
Mass right and in the Episcopal Church
sometimes they call
communion uh but this was my favorite
time and uh and I got to be an altar boy
so I was always hanging out with the
priests you know you get to go in these
little rooms in the front and you feel
really special and um we had really
beautiful really fantastic priest one of
them was um he had been a Trapper in
Alaska really rough big guy and uh one
day he got snowed into his cabin right
and it was way over the roof of the
cabin and he was many miles from
anywhere and he he was going to die in
the cabin so he got down on his knees
you know this Traer and he uh he prayed
and he said God if you if you save me
I'll become a pisal
priest so some guy came du him out and
uh he had to you know honor his word so
he became a priest and he was a father
Paulo he was very beautiful man and uh
so I remember one morning
uh we we had 7:30 service we had 9:00 9
7:30 9:15 and 11 11 was for the lazy
people and they did didn't get much uh
Eucharist cuz they were lazy and then uh
9:15 you got it twice a month uh
Eucharist you know and then the the 7:30
people always got Eucharist CU they got
up so early they were working harder uh
so you know I was the alter boy and and
we we got there a little early me and my
brother and we were waiting in the side
room and and you do this big thing back
there with the Eucharist you know that
the father pulls out the the holy wine
uh from somewhere and uh he has these
special bows and special chales and then
they pull out these in my church it was
little
rapers and they were really special you
know like you you didn't even want to
touch one you know it's like so holy uh
just to be around them was a
blessing and I remember uh one
morning uh we were doing the 7:30
service and um we got everything ready
and then you make this grand entrance
right the father has all these U black
CAC on and different colors of uh stalls
for different holidays and you know and
it was really a big deal when we made
our entrance and then I had this stupid
red
bow
girl but it was
okay I really like to be a and uh I
thought it was such an honor so so we we
came out um in the right here and we
made our big entrance you know and then
we looked out and there wasn't anybody
there there wasn't a single person in
ch and talking
a people and we look out at the Sea of
no faces and uh and then me and my
brother are like like this you know
because hey we get to go home you know
maybe we can catch some cartoons after
years something we were really Happ you
know and uh then the priest father he
turns to us and he says you know you
know God Jesus said when one or two are
gather
together so we're going to do the
ma so you know he said we're going to go
ahead and we're going to do it you know
and we did a whole thing we word every
single word you know everything perfect
and uh we were the me and my brother
were the only communic you know and it
was so beautiful it was just so
beautiful uh to get
um to be granted uh the body of blood
Christ you know and then he didn't care
that nobody was there he just thought it
was important to do you know so it's
really really beautiful so I never
forget
so I I thought to tell you what what I
was thinking about when I got it when I
was a teenager okay and then I thought
maybe some of you could tell me what you
think and then we could go from there
okay cuz you know what's happening when
you take this uh little piece of bread
which didn't taste very good uh and it
was too dry it's stuck in your mom stuck
on the top of your mom and but I thought
it was really holy and I tried to keep
it like half the day
talk and I just suck it from time to
time you know I would eat it you know
right away I just keep it there uh I'm
Stu to the top of M and then uh take the
the the Holy One right
and I
I I didn't have any clear idea what was
going on you see I I'm just saying what
I felt you know I didn't particularly
think uh oh I'm Jesus's body I didn't
think that even though they told us over
and over when you're getting it you know
and then I took the wine and it wasn't
so much for me uh Jesus's blood it for
I'm just saying honestly what it was for
me it was um just something very holy
and it put me into a very very deep
place and I felt like I was in God's
hand or something and
uh and it was just like that that's all
you know it wasn't anything else
uh it was done you know and we went to
to take communion in my church you had
to go through um what's it called Cate
catechism confirmation class you had to
take a class and then they explained to
you what what was going on you you
couldn't take the I mean little kids
came up and God little Knuck little uh
but you had to go through training and
you had to know what you were doing and
Bishop Hart came and you you know gave
us catechism and you know that was
a a big step in your life but but from
all that
training uh what I actually felt in my
heart uh when it was coming
down uh was just like to be in the
presence of Jesus at some point okay
like that was like a way to be in the
presence of Jesus and it felt very very
beautiful so I wanted to ask uh I just
ask four or five people who have Christ
and those who don't have courage I want
to hear from you
first and you don't have to stand up for
anything you can just yell out and maybe
nobody will see you okay uh well maybe
we should have some order I don't know
but what what did you feel at when you
got the bread and the wine how what
happened what did you
think
now for
for me the Episcopal Church changed many
years ago to welcome infants to the
communion that the moment you were
baptized you were welcomed to
communion because it was the Phil became
the philosophy as the church grew in
wisdom I would think that as we eat food
for our body that the Eucharist is the
food for our soul
so that one doesn't have to take a class
you don't take a class to learn to
eat or to know how to chew the carrot or
you just do it and it became the
philosophy that it's that way with
Eucharist and that's the way it's always
felt for me that my soul is hungering
for a closer relationship to God and
that that Holy meal
becomes the food for my soul yeah did
everybody hear did you hear okay yeah so
I used to think of it as gas
station uh like every week you go back
to the gas station and you get uh filled
up and then you can last another week
and it's not like normal food you have
to eat two or three times a day but uh
comunion or mass you I felt like you
needed it once a week and then I felt
like it was going to the gas station for
my spirit and
getting getting refilled so I can get
through the week something like that
yeah okay anybody else want to chat go
talk loud okay they can't hear uh the
way I feel about it is that that is a
moment in time where where there's
presence God is present and um that
presence is not only there for me to
experience but somehow God sees
me that's it okay so God's
presence I think so yeah that that
somehow when you go come up and you
kneel down and the thing touches your
your tongue or your lips you feel like
like then you must be in God's presence
yeah yeah anybody
else there's one but you have to run
over talk loud
umit growing up in the Methodist Church
we just believe that the bread and the
wine were two symbols so I didn't really
give it I didn't
I just gave them my attention as if
something was supposed to
happen say it again I didn't cat the uh
The Bread and Wine they're just simply
dool
yeah then what did you say about
attention well I would taste the wine
and look for something to happen Okay
anything El
or tast sweet
maybe one more anybody
anybody uh
do you have to talk loud okay um I
actually grew up Jewish so
my experience with communion was when I
got invited to go with a friend and um
didn't know I wasn't supposed to go
up and the thing that was confusing to
me was that in the Jewish tradition was
any thing between me and God there was a
very personal relationship and so at the
time my experience of it was it was
actually something not a bridge but
something that I didn't understand that
actually got between me and a a very
personal relationship so it's very
interesting I'm really excited to hear
this different view of it yeah I think
one more my my teacher
for me it was the symbol
of
transformation that something could be
one thing and become another
thing and then so for me that meant I
could
be flawed or hurt and then healed so
that the transformation was possible for
me too yeah
good so let's talk there and and talk
about that cuz uh Laura was talking
about what do it call it trans is it
Transfiguration is it just trans trans I
don't know but at some point in the in
the in the
ceremony uh the the wine or the great
juice depending on which the church you
grew up in uh is set to become the blood
of Christ and then the the the bread is
set to be the body of Christ change into
uh actually change into during the
ceremony right so I I was talking at a
church last night in Phoenix uh St Peter
it's really beautiful and very nice
people and um you know I was I was
telling them about my first experience
uh I you know you find out more about
your religion when you go elsewhere and
then you look back at your religion
right so I was I went to I went had a
chance to study in the
Himalayas and uh there were llamas there
the D Lama was close by
and there were uh great llamas there and
I was like 19 or 20 or something like
that you know and I I went to study at
the D place and they were just opening
up to foreigners and it was difficult
because not many people spoke English
and and then I I I remember uh sitting
in a small Stone room with this llama
you know and we were talking and I would
keep asking questions about Buddhism and
then and then I said he said well let me
ask you a question you know and I said
okay and he said um um I heard there's
this guy named yesu okay they call him
yeshu and uh you know that there's this
religion that Yu started and I heard
some weird things about it you know and
can you explain it to me you know can
you just answer some questions you know
so I said okay and he said well first of
all who's yeshu you know I said well
yeshu is called Jesus and and he founded
this religion called Christianity cuz
they're from Tibet they just got out
tobet they never met a Christian uh
which is unusual in the world
and and they came out and and he said I
said well you know he was a great
teacher he teaches a lot of the same
things that you teach about compassion
and wisdom and he was a really great
teacher and then he then they said well
he got he got murdered right and I said
yeah he he was killed uh he was executed
by the religious authorities of his time
and then uh they said well what's this
cross thing anyway you know why do you
why do you use a cross you know and I
said well actually that's that's the
thing he was killed on he was nailed to
that uh cross and so he took the cross
as uh the symbol of our religion you
know then he looks at me in this weird
look and he says you know that's like
using an electric chair for your symbol
you know I mean this was uh you know
this is the worst moment in your
religion's history and the most painful
moment in the Founder's life and the the
hardest moment you know the moment of
greatest pain and you take as your
symbol the the you know we take a wheel
us Buddhists we have a wheel you know
said well what's the wheel mean he says
it's teaching that the teaching goes
from generation to generation like a
wheel and the Buddha turns the wheel and
then it's turned by each generation so
that's sort of a happy positive symbol
um but you guys this this cross thing
you know why do you why do you use a
cross you know and I then I said well
uh you know we believe that on the cross
uh Jesus died and then he made a sort of
a deal a covenant right we got sort of a
deal came down and uh he said uh his
death voluntary death on the cross as a
Divine being his willingness to die on
the cross uh would be in exchange for
all the bad Deeds Done by all of
humanity forever you know like one one
person's death uh would
suffice uh one Divine person's death
would suffice to clean the bad Deeds of
all all later all generations in time
you know if they believed in him so I
said so we don't see this cross as a bad
thing you know we see it as a good thing
a deal was made on that day and an
exchange was made and we are kind of
happy about the exchange you know we
thought it's a good thing you know so we
took it as our symbol then then they
said the weirdest thing we heard about
your church about your religion and they
they're not Tibetans won't speak to you
frankly for a long time you know when
you become their friend like if you show
yourself to be a good person for like a
year then they'll ask you these
questions otherwise they'll just polite
all the time and they don't say anything
you know at all that might offend you
you know but after you get to know them
for like a year they start grilling you
you know so so he was like but the
weirdest thing I heard I said go ahead
you can you can be frank you know he
said this thing about eating his body
drinking his blood I mean this is your
founder of your religion and you're like
chewing on his fingers and and sucking
out his blood and this is weird you know
this is really strange you know and I
said well it's not exactly like that I
said you know we we take um a symbol of
his body his blood you know the the
bread and the wine you know so he said
oh well then it's not the body and bl I
said well you know something happens
when they're up in the ceremony and then
it becomes the body and blood this is
like they're Debaters right Buddhists
are Debaters so he's like oh so you do
eat the body and you do drink the blood
the founder of your religion you know
and it's so cannibalistic you know
they're like they were really shocked
you know and and then I I spent like
months trying to explain to them what
was going on you during the Eucharist
you know and it was hard to explain to
someone who never heard of a Christian
uh what's going on with the Eucharist
that was hard so they said well how did
it start how did all this stuff start
and I said well there was you know the
night before he was he died uh he had a
dinner with all his students his
disciples and and they all ate together
and he knew he was going to dies and he
knew it was the last dinner you know so
he called at all of them together and
they had a dinner together you know
and then uh the the Llama asked me well
you know what were the disciples doing
if they knew he was in trouble or might
be killed the next day why why weren't
they doing anything why were they
talking about it the last summer you
know I said
well there was sort of argument going on
about who would be remembered as the
greatest disciple later on you know and
they're like are you kidding
me the head of the religion is about to
be murdered and the disciples are like
sneaking him off to another country and
something and and they're like arguing
about who's going to be the greatest
who's going to be remembered as the
greatest you know I said well I wasn't
exactly like that but um Jesus then
Jesus said he sat down and he said uh Le
F right I have to show off I studied
some biblical Greek a while ago so Le f
means take eat okay Le F if you care
here uh leg comes from it's all from
Sanskrit Eucharist is from Sanskrit okay
u u is the Greek for good which came
from ESU in Sanskrit which is shortened
to Su which means good like suata or
suganda or
Suka okay and then uh Kus Kus comes from
her her what's her heart heart so it
means the word UK means good heart okay
it means the good heart you you ciss and
uh it comes from India the words come
from India okay and and what it the word
Eucharist means is I give thanks it came
to mean I give thanks and then uh the
first thing Jesus did at the
dinner you know he got up and said I'd
appreciate if everybody stopped arguing
and um I we're going to have a special
ceremony you know and he said Le f took
uh he took the breath and said take F
comes from uh
Sanskrit uh B okay the F in Greek comes
from or the pH in Greek comes from BH in
Sanskrit the E comes from an a uh the G
comes from a g it's B like
ban uh it's a direct derivative of the
word for Buddha okay uh Baga means uh
take your share or bite something okay
so Le
is just a corrupt Sanskrit for uh take
eat you know and Jesus said take eat and
I don't know the way I was brought up uh
this is
my body which is given for you for the
Forgiveness of sins do this as often as
you shall do this as often as you shall
do this in remance do this in
remembrance of
me so basically what Jesus is saying the
way I learned it you know I don't know
if it's precise but um the way I learned
it was at the Last Supper Jesus is
offering uh bread he breaks bread he
says huko he says let us give thanks you
know and then he then he um says this is
my body you know and then uh which is
which is given for you you know and eat
let it f it take and eat it and then he
says
uh do this as off as you eat right every
time you take bread then think of me
okay in the future uh later on uh when
you're taking bread then think of me you
know just remember me you know and then
he says the same thing with the wine he
says you know take drink uh this is my
blood which is given for you and for
many for the Forgiveness of sins do this
as often as you shall drink it in
remembrance of me right so he's saying
um now take the
and and drink it to remember me okay to
remember me all right
[Music]
so and you have to realize one thing
wine in those days uh why were they
drinking
wine because the water was not healthy
the water was not drinkable okay I mean
water in olden times was not drinkable
when I first went to my Monastery when I
was first
ordained uh we they were all refugees
they were all living in tents and uh I
said I'm thirsty you know and they
brought me a glass of water it was brown
it was like a dark brown like the pews
you know and I and I said well you know
frankly I I mean in all due respect I
don't think I can drink that and they
looked at me you know and they said you
don't have any choice you know that's
the only water here that's the only
water within 50 miles you know you have
to drink it you don't have a choice you
know that will make you sick it will
make you sick but we you don't have any
other water and you drink it in those
days you drink it you know
so so it's not that they're like
drinking wine like the way we drink wine
they're drinking they're drinking wine
because that's what the main beverage at
meal at a meal so it be like drinking
water I mean it be like drinking water
and then what I what I Feel Jesus was
saying was that um every time you eat
anything and every time you drink water
or any liquid anytime then you remember
me okay you stop and you think of your
teacher you know you you stop and think
of me uh every time you every time you
eat put anything in your mouth every
time you ever take a drink of anything
pause and think of me you know think of
think of me but then the hard part is
that's okay right we call inet it's
called Dem deak means
a an artificial reminder throughout the
day of your teacher's kindness or
something like that you know this is
reab the reab the rabbi's kindness right
which is a big deal in those days the
reason the disciples were always around
him is because it was customary not to
leave the rabbi sign for his whole life
uh so so by taking the bread and
drinking the wine they would would have
every time they had water they would be
thinking of their Revit of their teacher
right they would think of their teacher
um but the thing the I the thing I was
hoping to speak
about and what really nobody mentioned I
think I
mean well partly it's the transformation
thing right like what
happens does it really change you know
does the wine that we're going to be
honored to have tonight due to Reverend
mcde coming um he's going to serve us uh
communion you know does the wine
actually change just before reaches your
lips or when the priest performs the
ceremony does the wine change into a
Divine being's love and does the little
wafer piece of bread change into that
being's body and what happens to you
when you take it you see if it did
change then what would happen to if you
took it so let's talk about those two
things Okay can it change into something
else and then secondly if it was
somebody's blood and body of a Divine
being what would happen to you what
would it do to you if you took it right
so
yeah
okay uh are you going to talk about
Ken the two questions you just ask yeah
but I'm only talking about the first
question first question yeah can it
change does it change the claim isn't
that the physical appearance changes the
claim is that from ainus where it ran
through that the substance changes
and it appears in any way physically
appears um and in that way just as
Christ's blood is he didn't really
finish what happens after after the
cross um but the resurrection is the
atone not just the atonement but also
the entrance of the Holy Spirit into a
person's life for transformation for
actually changing so the and the the
episc tradition carries us through that
the um the change in the substance of
the bread and blood Bread and Wine is
actually changing to
carry the grace which Christ imparts to
us he imparted through us to us through
the cross the gift of salvation
salvation for our soul to live a better
life and this is um just like that the
continuing feeding of our soul of our
spirit with um the bond with a physical
remembrance that really affects us
emotionally cool okay
all right so back to my first
question
uh I mean yeah I would say I mean we
nobody would say the physical form
changes doesn't change right
but you know last night in Phoenix the
the priest priest gay she asked me uh
could you explain these two ideas about
Buddhism that we heard one is called
emptiness one is called karma you know
we we heard these two ideas and can you
explain what they
mean so you know I was getting into the
emptiness of me young okay and uh and I
said well the best example empist I can
think of is Neil Young you know because
uh when I hear Neil Young I think it's
the most fantastic thing I ever heard
you know I mean pre1 1970 Neil
Young okay and then I remember when I
took my new album which I refused to let
out my hand the whole way to go to
college on the East Coast uh I played it
there for my roommate I said you know
you're lucky you're four years with me
now I'll have Neil Young every night
singing to you know and he says well I
never heard of this guy could you put it
on and I put on Neil Young and he said
um he he had this look on his face you
know and then I said at the end of
cowgirl on the S I said so how did you
like it you know he say he said he
sounds like a screaming unic you know
and and then uh we had this big fight uh
the whole four years you know I wasn't
allowed to play the album unless he was
out of the room
and so that's a good example of
emptiness okay emptiness means that uh
Neil Young can sound good or Neil Young
can sound bad uh sounding good is not
inside of Neil Young and sounding bad is
not inside of Neo sounding good is not
coming from NE and sounding bad is not
coming from neong if sounding good was
coming from neong the way he played then
everyone would enjoy neong see and if
sounding bad was coming from Young I
wouldn't have bought his album okay like
that so what we say is that sounding
good doesn't belong to Neon and sounding
good doesn't belong to neong either so
where's it where's it coming from if I
enjoy neon and somebody else hates neon
where's that coming from if it's not
coming from Neon cuz if it was coming
from Nong everyone would feel the same
about Nong in the way that we all
experience the p in as the same kind of
word see so what where is it coming from
what's the other
choice yeah Barb said it's coming from
us okay so it's coming from us so if you
want to know what emptiness means it
means that nothing is the Way It Is by
itself uh it's it's the way it is is
coming from us if you like the young
it's coming from you if you don't like
it's you okay
um so can I just decide to like uh
what's that guy's name idiot Smith
Elliot
Smith and I just decide that I would
like you know can I just say oh G
Michael was in the church the other
night and he said everything is coming
from me
so therefore I will just decide to like
this guy that I can't stand you know and
then you play it and you you decide I'm
going to like
it and it doesn't work you know so so
does that mean it's not coming from
us does that mean it's not coming from
us it is say again we're stubborn yeah
or we're stuck with it okay yeah we're
stuck with it okay like the way you hear
it is coming from you but you don't seem
to have a choice you see what I mean you
can't control it in the present moment
okay gar it you can't say I'm going to
like idiot Elliot Smith okay you're just
stuck with the way you hear okay why and
that's when you get into Karma okay
that's when you get into karma karma
means if you treat other people kindly
let's say if you speak kindly to other
people right if you're careful to only
speak kindly to other people that puts a
seed in your mind that plants a certain
seed in your mind
uh that seed may stay in the mind for a
week or a month or a year okay depending
on other thought the the seed is planted
in your mind and then when you hear Neo
young if you've been speaking
kindly that seed opens in your mind and
you experience Neil Young as as pleasant
as sounding good okay why cuz you
sounded good to others you spoke kindly
to others that's Karma okay Karma needs
another person you you need someone to
bounce Karma off so so if you hear a
song that's being sounding good it's
because you spoke kindly to other people
and then later when you turn on the
radio and Neil Young comes on it sounds
good to you okay and then the opposite
happens if you are unkind to people if
you say mean things to people or you say
angry things to people then then when
you turn on music it doesn't sound good
to you it doesn't matter what music you
turn on it doesn't sound good to you
that's how coming from you but the seed
is planted in your mind and the seed
opens and you don't have control over
that process okay once the seed breaks
open uh my teacher used to say it's like
you can't take it back you can't ask the
The Way NE young sound to go back into
the seed you can't push a tree back in
the ground okay you you do something it
plants a seed in your mind and then the
consequences of what you did as you what
as you s so shall so shall you reap I
mean this is Jesus also okay whatever
you plant in your own Spirit your own
heart you must it must come out it must
come back to you it and whatever you
plan will come back to you that way
so how you hear NE young is coming from
you but you don't have control anymore
because that seed was planted 6 months
ago you can't you can't stop the scene
and you can't decide how this song is
going to sound okay
got it things are empty Neil Young
doesn't sound good Neil Young doesn't
sound bad Neil Young is a bunch of a
bunch of sounds just a bunch of random
sounds whether you hear it good or bad
depends on how kind you've been to
others if you've spoken kindly to others
you'll hear n sounding good if you
spoken unkindly to others you'll hear
something bad okay what's that got to do
with the Eucharist
it is what you make it's what you bring
to it it's what your seeds make them
okay cuz we said I can't make it you see
so we say the bread and the wine we say
they are empty in the sense that they
are blank like a blank screen
okay they could be normal
wheat you know they could just be normal
bread and they could be normal wine they
they could be that okay but they could
also be the body and blood of a Divine
being okay G it who makes them either
one who makes neon
good it's me okay got it and we would
say the Eucharist the the bread and the
wine are blank okay they're not they're
not a Divine thing and they're not
something that was bought in the at
saway this afternoon okay right they're
not normal and they're not divine by
themselves they're just stuff it's just
stuff it's a round brown thing and a red
liquid thing okay then how you
experience it what it becomes for you
it's coming from you okay you it could
be divine it could be something Divine
it could be
transformed or it could be just uh
regular bread regular wine okay how do
you transform it
then it's more fun can we agree that
it's more fun to drink of a Divine
being's Flesh and Blood than it is to
just have a hammer her I mean can we say
that we would prefer as you said to have
the blessing and the grace imparted to
us from a Divine substance right so we
would rather that the bread and the wine
were divine than just something that you
picked up at saway this afternoon you
know by the way both are
there both are always there it could go
either way Sam the Safe Way is there and
Jesus is there and which way it goes
depends on what as you
so so sh so if you if you are kind to
others if you take care of
others as you
would yourself yourself if you take care
of other people as well as you would
yourself that puts a seed in your
mind that that you see this substance as
Divine and someone said sitting next to
you who hasn't taken care of other
people how do they see it they get
really disappointed they see the they
see the plastic Peter wrapping from
Safeway and they say oh my God they
didn't even make this in a Christian
Factory or anything we should pick this
up at Safeway this morning you know they
see the rapper and they feel they feel
like disappointed somehow I remember
when I was you know a kid you you get to
go in the priest's room you know and
they're just unwrapping some bread from
Safeway you're like wait a minute I
thought this came from heaven or
something you know and and
uh so both breads are there got it the
bread is there regular old Peter from
Safeway is there and Jesus's body is
there and which one comes to you which
way you experience it comes from
what comes from what yeah how you take
care of other people okay how you take
care
of so can we say that the that the
substance can be transformed
yeah Neil Young a screaming unit can
become the best rock star in the world
you know didn't you see the Canadian
americ playoff on last Sunday where the
Canadians cheated and beat the
Americans so you know they're not like
who are they focusing in on on in the
crowd it's NE young you know
uh so
the substance can go either way if you
want the substance to be
divine you have to be kind to others
that charges the substance that changes
the substance okay you have to be good
to others and ideally although it's not
possible for us right as as good as you
would be for yourself okay so we hang on
come afterwards ideally we can say that
the substance can be transformed it can
be I'm just saying I was charged with
giving a Buddhist perspective on the
Eucharist so a Buddhist mon g would say
yes the substance can be transformed it
can become the body of Christ and the
blood of Christ and it can have the
power and the blessing and the grace
when you particular of Christ entering
you okay but what about the second part
and then I'll shut up then we then we'll
have a Eucharist okay what's the second
part uh take eat this is my my body
that's given for you and for others
for the Forgiveness of sins okay so now
this is a big question if you now now we
get into debate okay now it'll be a
debate uh you know a Buddhist would have
to
say that everything in your life every
experience every person you ever meet
your income your health the condition of
your spouse or your partner or your
children or your mother or any other
person you ever met in your life is a
direct reflection of how you're treating
other people Karma okay there there's no
experience that you have in your whole
life good or bad animate or inanimate
living or dead right there's no thought
in your mind even that doesn't come from
how you treat other people all things in
your life come directly from how much
kindness you have shown other people so
if you don't show kindness to
others you will you will not be happy
it's not possible because every person
you ever
meet every building you ever sit in
every thought that passes through your
mind is a direct result of how much
kindness you show other people that's
that's karma that's the law of karma
okay but there's a second law of
karma it can only be collected by an
individual okay it cannot be
transferred that's a L Karma I cannot be
kind for you you see what I mean I can't
go and and help IM illegal imigrants who
need water I if I if I go and serve
water to an illegal immigrant on the
border right if I sit there and wait for
them and then serve them right I put a
certain seed in my mind to that action a
certain seed of karma is planted in my
soul through that action and I cannot
transfer it to another person it's not
possible understand I can't give you my
good deeds I you have to do your own
Good Deeds what the Buddhist proof for
that is interesting okay like there has
to be a proof right uh in Buddhism you
need a proof the proof of that that no
one can give you Karma or take your
karma right no one can give you a seed
and no one can take a seed from you it's
proved by the fact that that we still
suffer okay it's proved by the fact that
we still suffer
we're still getting old we still go
through sickness life is a long series
of disappointments for the few people
who who collect some money and have a
nice family and find a good wife and
have nice children and get a good job
and don't get laid off for the very few
of like that then what
happens they die they lose it all so
it's all like this useless exercise you
see we are suffering we are in
a impossible situation
we're in an airplane that must crash you
know life is a living life is sitting in
an airplane which must crash and you
must die right so it's useless it's a
failure if it were possible to Grant
someone else your your your goodness
right or if it were possible to take it
their pain away from them I I Michael
Roach wouldn't be suffering today I
wouldn't have had doubts and problems
today I wouldn't have been tired in the
afternoon I would would have slipped on
the Christine's garage and fall down
today you know it wouldn't have happened
why if it was possible to take away my
my negative
seeds any any Divine being would have
taken it before I wouldn't be here I
wouldn't be in a place like this I
wouldn't be getting all you know I I I
wouldn't be suffering I wouldn't have
fallen down today if it were possible
for for someone to look at me and say oh
guess you Michael you're going to fall
down today that's a seed that you got
from hurting someone when you're a k
here I'll take it out of your mind for
you you know I see that you're going to
fall down today I take the seat out so
so a Buddhist philosopher says it's not
possible to give another person the
seeds of your kindness or to transfer
their suffering to you not possible
because karma is collected by the
individual you don't get in trouble if I
step on a bug I get in trouble it
wouldn't be fair right it wouldn't be
fair to say oh I I I killed a cop today
and and Andrea lemon has to I'm going to
give you the result okay like you you
should suffer in six months okay like
you can't give away stuff like that it
it sticks with you what you do good what
you do bad sticks with you what's that
got to do with the
Eucharist why is K Michael bringing this
up about the Eucharist
Le F take eat this is my body which is
given for you and for others for forg
the Forgiveness of
sins are you going to take away my seeds
you know if I partake of this wine
tonight and if I partake of this bread
tonight uh can you guarantee me that
I'll never slip again on Christine
Walsh's Caro
can you take away my can you forgive my
sins is it possible that this is the
second question we had two questions
right first was can you transform the
stuff
yes you it can become a Divine being's
body and blood and therefore ultimately
worthy to partake of any anybody would
want to partake of it or you're a fool
what's the second
one is it is it possible then for the
forgiveness for you and for others for
the Forgiveness of sins that's the that
was the word right for you and for
others for the Forgiveness of sins is it
possible for but that by partaking of
this substance tonight you know that
something happens to you and your sins
are forgiven is it
possible can if I if I drink this wine
and I eat this bread which has been
changed into the body of Christ
can you guarantee to me that I that that
my sins have been clean and I won't have
any suffering tomorrow will it
happen huh that goodness yeah yeah he
gave a good answer
okay uh hang on one second but it's a
good it's coming
uh Neil Young sounding good is not in
the song got it sounding bad is not in
the song being Divine flesh is not in
the bread being bread is not in the
bread okay if if you experience it as
bread tonight it's because you weren't
very nice to other people If you
experience it as a Divine being's
flesh that's because you've been kind to
other people okay now that's the
emptiness of the bread and that's the
emptiness of the wine and that's the
emptiness of milon got it what about the
emptiness of forgiving
sins what about that can the can the
substance have the power to remove your
sins and and if it does who put it
there yeah you okay it would be you I
think the thing I'm struggling with what
you're saying H don't don't don't I'm
just getting
them later I got to keep on the straight
thought listen to and I'll list what was
I thinking
yeah okay sounding good is not put is
not inside Milan song being Jesus's
flesh is not inside the bread being
Jesus's blood is not inside the blood if
you experience it as Jesus's blood if
you experience it as Jesus's flesh it's
because you've been kind to others got
it right just say right agree
with now whether or not it has the
potency to to to clean you of your bad
deeds in the Bible right bad
deed whether or not it's capable whether
or not it has the potency to remove your
sins where would that come from
According
to like everything else is coming from
me
how yeah if I'm good to others I've
forgiven them yeah exactly
oh
yeah she said it if I have been forgiven
of
others if I forgive others their
trespasses how's it go for
again right please forgive me as I
forgive those who trespass against us
which is why we haven't been
forgiven because we don't forget that's
right okay so she said a beautiful thing
I mean that's the the whole thing that's
the whole thing whether the blood and
the body has the power to forgive you
your sins right depends on what if you
forget how well do you forgive others
you know how well do you forgive others
there's an interesting thing in the
Bible Jesus is a rabal Jesus is a real
rabal you know he doesn't debate whether
war is good or bad you know he's not
talking about
that he's saying if someone slugs you on
the left side of your face
what ask them if they want to slug you
on the right side of your face you blew
up the world train Center would you like
to do the Empire State
Building that's what he's saying that's
he's not talking should you invade Iran
or just a rap or or should you just
boyot or you know he's not suggesting
that if someone steals your sweater what
does he say give me a coat too hey are
you the guy who stole my sweat he looks
a l looks like a lot like my sweater
that I left in the church the other
night you know and they said yeah I
swiped it they said you mean you didn't
even just think it was left there you
swiped it I said yeah I swiped it well
would you like my pants too you know I
mean Jesus is Jesus is super radical
Jesus is super radical so on the subject
of forgiveness what's he saying forgive
everything forgive everything and
anything you know we have we forgive on
two levels one are forgivable things on
one are unforgivable
things and you know you have done a
forgivable thing to me you know like you
insulted my cheesecake the other day and
I forgive
you but you broke up with me last month
and that's unforgivable I mean that's
going too far you know there's certain
things I can forgive there's certain
other things I can't forgive as long as
you
hesitate in your capacity for
forgiveness
a Buddhist a Buddhist Viewpoint of the
Eucharist is that it cannot work on you
you can eat the blood you can bite the
body and nothing's going to happen you
you'll go home and be as sad tomorrow as
you were today you see nothing will
change because your sins will not be
forgiven because you have not forgiven
others okay and I would assert you know
that that's exactly what Jesus said you
know in the Lord's pray you know forgive
us our trespasses as we forgive those
who trespass against us you know um
equal what do you call right you know I
accept from God the Covenant I accept
this deal you will only do whatever
kindness to me that I do to others you
know what did Jesus say you know you
didn't visit me in prison you know right
he said whatever I H yeah so God is in a
way God is saying Jesus is saying my
ability to take away your sins my
ability to forgive you is limited to the
amount you forgive others that's a
Buddhist Viewpoint okay that's a radical
Viewpoint okay I would assert that's
what Jesus said I would assert that what
Jesus said so final question then we'll
actually have some wine and bread or
body and
blood
uh is there any like what do you call it
exemptions you know I mean come on I
can't forgive
everybody personally I can't do it
people hurt me and I I I keep it for a
long time there's a separate word in
tobet called SBA which means slow
burning I have siga you know someone
hurts me I got siga I don't say anything
I still get up and give nice talks and
I'm very reasonable in class and
everything I can sit there and pretend
to mate everybody thinks I am
inside I have Tia you know how could
they do this to me how could they do
this to me I will never forgive them
like that right I have it I don't I
don't know if we are
capable of of forgiving to the amount
that we need to be forgiven you see I
mean I don't think it's a good
deal I I don't think it's a good deal if
Jesus said you're only going to get as
many sins taken away from you as you
forgive other people for bad stuff they
do to you I'm in trouble you know is
there any easy way
you know is there
any can you sort of just get everything
cancelled you know can you go to
somebody and say look I can't forgive as
well as as well as you want us to
forgive I can't do it I'm just not
capable of it and I assert that we're
not at least I'm not you know I'm just
not capable enough to be forgiving as
you want me to be for the blood and body
to work
tonight okay is there a catch 22 can you
get out of this problem
we say belief we say we say belief okay
that's the last thing I'll say can
I how many last
things uh we a Buddhist philosopher in
strict accordance with the scriptures of
Buddhism could
say if you believe in N right that this
being is divine if you take them as your
true teacher right for us it would be
our our root lum
would be our heart number for a
Christian it would be Jesus right if you
accept
them as your heart
teacher the karma of God is enough to
transform the Stu and the karma of God
is enough to wipe out your sins you see
if if you totally believe in them if you
really believe they are Divine if you
believe they are like an angel right we
would say an angel a if you believe
believe enough the karma of the effect
on your mind would be to remove your
your your Bad
Karma uh forgive your sins see just just
believing in your heart mama or your or
Jesus in your case the Christian case
it's Jesus we would say heart mama
enough devotion enough faith in the
power of your heart mama is enough to
make the bread and white work okay and
you don't have to be Christian to take
it okay you can partake it if your faith
is enough if your belief is enough as
you partake it yeah it could clean your
it could clean away all your bad seeds
in your mind then what happens the next
day your life is beautiful more
beautiful than it was before okay it
doesn't all happen in one day okay
Buddhism says you don't get all your
negative you don't get all your sins
forgiven in one sip of wine
blood uh you have to keep coming back
and and you have to keep building your
faith but if you have enough belief in
your heart teacher in Jesus and you take
something that you that you see as part
of them it's enough that's enough that's
all you need okay that's all
[Applause]
okay I I think now we're going to
celebrate the
Eucharist and uh everyone is welcome at
the table and
uh what you receive is entirely up to
you so on On Any Given Sunday uh what we
say as everyone's embodies to the table
to the altar to
receive if you're comfortable receiving
uh we ask that you cross your hands over
your chest and the priest will give you
a
blessing um if you open your mouth the
priest will place the host in your mouth
if you hold out your hands like this the
priest will put the the host in your
hand and then you can either dip or take
a sip from The Chalice when
com
so
uh what have I forgot
[Music]
was that clear so so this you get a
blessing if you open your mouth the
priest will put the host and the wine in
your mouth if you hold out your hands
you get the host which you can then eat
and take a sip in the Chalice or you can
dip the host in the
Chalice we don't have the just just give
the
[Music]
all right okay uh so apparently we don't
have the Chalice where the priest who
able to De so you'll get the host and
then you'll get the
one
um and uh so give us a few minutes to
get organized and then uh we'll have
everyone come and we'll Cate